Finding Aid for Eugene N. Feingold Papers, 1950-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eugene N. Feingold Papers 1950-2002, 1960-1990
Feingold, Eugene N.
5 linear feet
0469 Aa/2
Professor of Health Management and Policy at the University of Michigan School of Public Health; also active in the American Civil Liberties Union, Michigan League for Human Service, Corner Health Center, and other organizations promoting social justice issues. The collection consists of files relating to his activist interests and to his involvement with different committee memberships within and outside of the University of Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Professor Feingold (donor no. 7085 ) in various accessions between 1984 and 2003.
The collection is open to research.
Eugene Feingold served as a Professor of Health Management and Policy in the School of Public Health. He joined the University of Michigan in 1960, teaching Political Science, shortly after receiving his Ph.D. from Princeton. In 1966, he moved to the School of Public Health, where he taught on the politics of health care in addition to serving as the chair of the Department of Medical Care Organization from 1971-1977. In 1977, he became the associate dean of the Rackham Graduate School. He also served as the acting dean of the school.
Feingold was very active in organizations dealing with social justice issues: civil liberties, discrimination, and poverty. He was a member of the national board of directors of the American Civil Liberties Union. After becoming an emeritus professor he pursued a law degree which he received in 1992, in order to do pro bono work for the Michigan ACLU chapter.
Feingold worked to emphasize the human aspects of the scientific problems dealt with by health care organizations. To this end, he served as President of the American Public Health Association, as well as Chair of the Board of Directors for the Michigan League for Human Services. He was a member of the board of directors of M-CARE, U-M's managed care organization, and the Corner Health Center, a medical care and health education center for adolescents in Ypsilanti. He chaired the advisory committee of the University of Michigan Robert Wood Johnson Clinical Scholars Program until his death in October 2002 at the age of 71.
This collection reflects Eugene Feingold's interest in social justice issues and the many ways in which he served the community. It spans the period between 1950 and 2002, and has been divided in four series, Topical Files, Department of Medical Care Organization, University of Michigan Minority Concerns, Faculty against Institutional Racism (FAIR) and Ann Arbor Fair Housing Legislation.
Subjects:
Feingold, Eugene N.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Faculty Against Institutional Racism (University of Michigan); Racism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Social justice--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Minority Student Concerns Task Force.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medical Care Organization.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Feingold, Eugene N.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medical Care Organization.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (1950-2002) are a mixture of materials relating to various interests and activities of Eugene Feingold. They include extensive information on the Corner Health Center and the activities of its Board of Directors. Information on Michigan health care, race relations, and lecture notes for political science courses taught by Feingold are also included in this series.
  - Abortion 1985-1993 (Box 1)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Washtenaw County 1961-1998 (Box 1)
  - Bail Fund 1964 (Box 1)
  - Civil Disobedience 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Civil Liberties 1960-2002
    - Censorship 1967 (Box 1)
    - Internal Security 1960-1969
      - House Un-American Activities Committee 1961-1967 (Box 1)
      - Informants 1960-1969 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Cases 1952 (Box 1)
    - Religion 1965-2001 (Box 1)
    - Speech 1999 (Box 1)
    - Terrorism 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan 1960-1977 (Box 1)
  - Classified Research 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Wilbur 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Health Politics 1969-1986 (Box 1)
  - Corner Health Center 1981-2002
    - Corner Health Center 1981-2001 (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors Minutes 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Executive Director's Reports 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Federally Qualified Health Center Planning Meetings 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Financial Management Committee 1998-2002 (Box 1)
    - Investments 2000-2002 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Planning 1997-2002 (Box 1)
    - United Way 2000 (Box 1)
  - Cuba 1961 (Box 1)
  - Demonstrations 1964-1973 (Box 1)
  - Detroit 1985-2002 (Box 1)
  - Engler, John 1991-1995 (Box 1)
  - Gray Panthers 1987 (Box 1)
  - Gulf War 1991 (Box 1)
  - Hayden, Tom 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Ideology, Political 1961-1967 (Box 1)
  - Income Distribution 1998, undated (Box 2)
  - Meader, George 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Michigan
    - Budget 1981-2001 (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights 1945-1967 (Box 2)
    - HMO Task Force 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Public Assistance 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - Taxes 1963-2001 (Box 2)
    - Tax Case (Political Science 33) 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Michigan League of Human Services 75th Anniversary Dinner 1987 (Box 2)
  - Political Parties 1965-1983 (Box 2)
  - Political Science, Friedman Promotion 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Poverty 1969-1988 (Box 2)
  - Race Relations 1950-2000
    - Biological Differences 1964 (Box 2)
    - Black Power 1966-1968 (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Riots 1967-1970 (Box 2)
    - Education 1950-1989
      - Brown Case and the Supreme Court 1960-1965 (Box 2)
      - Colleges 1950-1989 (Box 2)
    - Family Structure 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Health 1987-2000 (Box 2)
    - Research Seminar 1966 (Box 2)
    - Preferential Treatment 1964-1998 (Box 2)
    - White House Conference 1966 (Box 2)
  - South 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Stratification 1958-1969 (Box 2)
  - Women 1972-1979 (Box 2)
- Department of Medical Care Organization
  Feingold's files from his work with the Department of Medical Care Organization (1963-1998) relate mostly to the administration of the department. These files reflect his work on various committees, his chairmanship of the department, as well as his administration of both the S.J. Axelrod and Beverlee Myers scholarships. Also included in this series are a number of student picture directories from the 1970's and 1980's.
  - Axelrod, S.J. 1974-1995 (Box 2)
  - Chairmanship 1970 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum 1970-1988
    - Master of Health Science Administration 1982-1988 (Box 2)
    - Master of Public Health 1970-1977 (Box 2)
    - Ph.D. 1963-1977 (Box 2)
  - Department Description 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Department Organization 1970 (Box 2)
  - Governing Body 1970-1985 (Box 2)
  - Minority Group Students 1969-1975 (Box 2)
  - Myers, Beverlee 1974-1998 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Policy, Master of Health Science Administration 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Promotions 1971-1987 (Box 3)
  - Recruiting 1967-1986 (Box 3)
  - Students 1969-1986 (Box 3)
- University of Michigan Minority Concerns
  The series University of Michigan Minority Concerns (1970-2000) consists of topical materials relating to minority relations on campus. The bulk of this series is made up of materials relating to the Minority Student Concerns Task Force, which Eugene Feingold chaired. This committee operated from 1979 to 1981 and was charged with examining minority student life at the university.
  - Black Action Movement 1970 (Box 3)
  - Harassment Policies 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Legal Advisory Council 1993-1999 (Box 3)
  - Minority Student Concerns Task Force 1976-1982
    - Coalition for the Utilization of Learning Skills 1976-1980 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Cost Estimates 1980 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Statements 1980 (Box 3)
    - Member Statements 1980 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Report 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Report Comments 1980 (Box 3)
    - Report Responses 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Research Literature 1979 (Box 3)
    - School and College Reports 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Student Statements 1980 (Box 3)
  - Racism 1988-2000 (Box 3)
- Faculty Against Institutional Racism (FAIR)
  Faculty Against Institutional Racism (FAIR) (1987-1992) was a group of mostly white faculty members that sought to educate the campus community and work toward a solution to racism at the University. This series consists of administrative materials (correspondence, meeting minutes, proposals) for the general group as well as for a subcommittee on elimination of discrimination in the classroom. Newspaper articles, speeches, and research materials are also included.
  - Correspondence 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Minutes 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1988 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Subcommittee 1988-1993
    - Budget and Proposals 1988-1993, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes
      - 1988-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- Ann Arbor Fair Housing Legislation
  - Clippings relating to fair hosing ordinance Ann 1962-1966 (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts of paper by Feingold and Lynn Eley entitled "No Progress Without Struggle: Fair Housing Legislation Come s to Ann Arbor" 1965 (Box 4)
  - Chronological Files
    - 1957-1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1963
      - January-February (Box 5)
      - March (Box 5)
      - April-May (Box 5)
      - June (Box 5)
      - July (Box 5)
      - August (Box 5)
      - September (Box 5)
      - October (Box 5)
      - November-December (Box 5)
    - 1964, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1966 (Box 5)
  - Fair Housing Ordinances (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor v. C. Frank Hubble 1964 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission (Box 5)
  - Listings of Ann Arbor Residents (Box 5)
  - Petitioners for the Advisory Vote of Fair Housing (Box 5)
  - Notes (Box 5)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - "The Negro in Local Government" by Ellen Bennett (Box 5)
  - Excerpt from Term Paper by Carol Siegel (Box 5)
  - "The Impact of Minority Status on Educational and Occupational Aspirations of School Children" 1963 (Box 5)